[Music]
in a world where technology is now
blamed for increased isolation
polarization and disconnection is it
reasonable to argue that tech could also
be the solution that's the idea behind
consciousness hacking I think when
people speak about consciousness hacking
they think of it as the tools and
strategies by which humans can alter
their own experience because there's a
lot more awareness now of the dangers of
technology people are starting to
realize the effect that social media and
mobile phones are having on our
attention spans and but you're sort of
taking a much more utopian view than
that you actually think that technology
can be the solution as well as the
problem maybe that's outlined what we
think the problem is first before we
could sure so I wouldn't I don't have a
utopian view I consider myself a techno
realist not oh not and and somewhere
between a techno realist and a techno
optimist and contingent upon certain
conditions changing our occurring
predicament is nothing less than a
disastrous in terms of how were
interacting with our technologies like I
wasn't even in the train the tube over
here today and I looked around me and it
was this dystopian and I just this
dystopian sense because I was on my left
was candy crush in front of me was
someone else playing candy crush in my
right was candy crush and then what we
we have to understand is the technology
has been designed to hack our dopamine
feedback loop response and as Tristan
Harris says it's a can have a race to
the bottom of the brainstem and were
people are people are engaging in these
swipes in order to elicit some sort of
neurological response without really
knowing why they're doing what they're
doing and this is that not the way
technology has to go I think if anything
this is antithetical to the deeper human
experience that where we are
[Music]
manipulating very basic human
vulnerability and using it in order to
basically sell more stuff and but but
the other thing is if you look at on a
train for example and I think what a lot
of people are using technology for is
essentially to move out from their
present experience the an uncomfortable
sensation may arise in the body and now
we don't know where like we no longer
have to sit with it instead we can
distract and get that dopamine hit and
that is very very problematic both from
a spiritual perspective in terms of
being able to really be okay with what
is but also from a societal perspective
we are to our current technological
landscape is creating fragile humans and
essentially traumatized ones we're
looking for these addictive dopamine
loops because we can't handle what is
it's almost like we're turning into
different kinds of creatures what does a
human being look like without an
attention span what does a human being
look like if they're constantly
distracted all the time that's a kind of
a mess experiment that's going on yeah
we we build our tools and then our - we
create our tools and our tools create us
yeah I mean ad D and concentration
difficulties are ubiquitous now and it's
because we're training our brains to
respond to higher and higher levels of
audio and visual stimulation so then I
no longer is a book sufficiently
adequate for the brain and body to be
satisfied with we need more and more as
it's addiction it's the same mechanics
of addiction that we see with drugs
we're seeing with tech we need more of a
stimulus to create the same response
this is a this is unser when I speak
about the the benefits of Technology I
want to emphasize the way it currently
is is not the thing it feels like
there's quite a lot of branching off
points here I mean the one the one thing
that I'm really struck by is daniel
trachtenberg who talks about this that
addiction is the most the the most
profitable form of capitalism or the
most
we'll form of relationship between any
business and its client if you can get
your customer addicted to something so I
know we'd like to kind of unpack it and
maybe talk about how technology might be
used in another way but isn't the deeper
question how in inherently exploitative
dynamic how can you move away from that
because all of the incentives are
leading in the other direction yeah no
it's a massive question and I think the
question and can we build not a
competitive as in when I'm usually were
competitive I mean I'm successful
non-addictive tools in a capitalist
system because ultimately are because of
our especially with mobile phone
software our profit models are based on
ad revenue an ad revenue is contingent
upon how much time the user is spent on
screen obviously if you're a company and
you're looking to maximize shareholder
value as is in your duty and profit
maximization and you can choose to to
have your your consumers in the screen
for 10 seconds versus 5 seconds you're
gonna choose the former it's it's built
into the economics and the set attention
economy is trust and in the center for
human technology speak to it and this is
a extremely distorting and so I think I
think ultimately what a new paradigm of
technology has to look like is some sort
of juxtaposition of a new tool with the
new system that doesn't just reward the
in which addiction isn't the inevitable
emergent outcome so and I'm interested
to hear you talk a bit more about those
technologies sort of the technological
side of things before maybe we sort of
swing back round to whether that's even
possible to shift wholesale towards that
within what you might call the game a or
a kind of rival hrus capitalist economy
yeah I want one thing I want to say a
big emphasis of consciousness hacking is
not really is is is not just what are we
building but really we're we building
from and we have to understand
that the things that we build and that
which we create are expressions and
extensions of us that we are building
tools that are dict
and tools that harm because our
consciousness is informing that creation
process we're creating and systematizing
and abstract things that are
disconnected from the heart because
we're building from a certain level of
rationality abstraction and logic I
think a big part of this consciousness
hacking movement is what woods
exponential creation look like if it
were built from the heart and to say
that differently if we do not start to
build from a more integrated place and
we continue to have many you know 25
year old programmers with exponential
capacities at their hands that's
catastrophic like that is not a good
thing we need to build our tools from a
deeper place a place of wisdom and I
think what you feel and what a lot of us
feel is that our tech process is so out
of alignment with deeper wisdom life's
natural flow that has to shift but for
that to shift we need to feel
reorientation for what Tech is all about
is it about extracting from the ground
in a linear way that isn't circular no
is it a bit addicting people no is it
about causing exponential species level
harm no for and it's out of alignment
with the deeper impulse of life and I
think we all feel that I think a lot of
people have there's resistance to
technology and it's a very intuitive
resistance it's plastic it's it's it's
not sustainable we need to be careful as
to what we are actually scaling and a
big part of what we focus on is let's
build from deeper and deeper places of
consciousness I'd love to get a few
examples I've heard you talk about this
before so lot to get some of the
examples of how tech could be used in a
different way or it or is being used in
a
different way yeah so I spoke just just
there to the inputs and detect where
we're building from and then we also
have to ask what what are we actually
building for the tools what we're
interested in is how do we make
technology actually nourishing to the
human being
let's see Tech is on a scale of -10 to
+10 -10 being it does utmost harm plus
10 saying it does like the art more good
a lot of our tech is probably a level of
maybe - 3 or minus 4 - the human
experience a lot of people are calling
for tech to be at a zero it's ethical
it's neutral or were saying is what
would it look like if tech actually
brought us closer together
deeper deepened our human experience and
helped to rather than hindered our
emotional psychological and spiritual
development and so for example you have
version 1.0 of a consciousness hacking
technology would be something like
biofeedback from meditation you wear a
brain a headband like the muse it gives
you audio signals as to whether or not
you're in a meditative state or not they
augments and encourages the meditation
process and you can actually massively
improve performance it's probably the
wrong word to use for meditation but
m-make the the the learning look more
effective so there's biofeedback tools
there's even headspace or waking up on
your phone as a meditation tech but
that's all just like version 1.0 of
what's out there
this is often called transformative
technologies version 2 there's some
really more advanced stuff coming out
right now
for example you've heard me speak before
about ultrasonic neuromodulation which
is ultra sound to the brain which j
Sanguinetti and shenzhen young the
meditation teacher is shenzhen and
cheese researcher researcher at
University of Arizona I'm assured that
isolating some very small ultrasound
waves to a very specific part of the
brain can lead to massive reductions in
internal now
and self rumination so the question is
you know if people are one in four
people in the UK have a mental health
disorder any one time what if they had
access to tools that could help to calm
down their nervous systems heal from
their trauma this stuff is actually
beginning to emerge that's on the mental
health side of things but then you also
look at the more systemic impact so for
example the climate change narrative is
failing right now because reason and
science doesn't seem to be getting
through in terms of that policy and I
think a large part of that is because
ideas and operate at one level but
experience can deepens into another and
so some studies have come out that show
that seeing a coral reef or one study in
particular seeing a coral reef and
decimate and virtual-reality
and one experience leads to the user
actually having a marked reduction in
things like energy consumption increase
in recycling months and months down the
line from that single experience you can
use the same BR for empathy things like
that so there are tools out there that
we can say okay what if we actually
harness this power for deeper and deeper
levels higher states and higher stages
of consciousness it's possible and it's
happening and the different framing of
that would be what if if we don't do
that we're we're just building tools
that are amplifying some of the most
basic human tendencies and pathologies
yeah I mean in my more positive moments
I can kind of think okay we've got we
had the first wave of tech and Facebook
Twitter they're reinforcing all of that
of the worst aspect and narcissistic
biases I desire to be seen I desire to
be validated and also optimizing for
outrage and for limbic hijack to keep us
on site and in all of these things sort
of and in my more optimistic moment oh
well that's not built into the tech
there it could be possible for example
to have a social media site based around
what we know about people's growth
patterns like how do you become more
open-minded how do you see more people's
perspectives how do you encounter views
that challenge what you think and lead
you to a more developed perspective on
etc etcetera all of these things could
be possible or designing it around yeah
a trajectory of growth individualized
for an individual person that for
example could be possible but then we
run into the difficulty of thinking but
the reason that these platforms are
optimized for this is because that is
what's rewarded attention is rewarded
outrages is makes for a sticky site that
means that people are interacting with
it and it seems difficult to see how
anything oriented towards a more
holistic vision for want of a better
word would be able to compete in a
marketplace with with a world that's
oriented around stickiness and outrage
and those features I agree it's it's
very very tough to imagine this given
the economic incentives that would there
suggest we are inevitably going
somewhere else but tech is like tech is
an amplifier the amplifiers skill and
amplifies as potency and where I've come
to with this argument is really my big
interest is in consciousness my but my
interest is more in the consciousness
piece I think than the actual tech piece
but I came to the conclusion that the
problems of the world are essentially
problems of human consciousness a
certain level of development and a
certain state of mind and things like
psychedelics meditation retreats lucid
dreaming a lot of these interventions
cannot a scale very effectively for
legal social religious time limitation
reasons Tech has this exponential
capacity to scale it's also abundance as
3d printing comes more and more in into
fashion and so the the the question is
is we have this capacity to scale tech
and if we were to reorient that towards
human flourishing then what kind of
world would we create and really it's
not gonna be easy and yet at the same
time tech companies work in hierarchies
and me living out in San Francisco in
the Bay Area
I really see hope and a lot of the
people with their fingers on power at
these companies are to some degree
waking up to a deepening of the
importance of a holistic approach so I
think if there is sufficient momentum
and drive from these leaders I think we
can start to create a change I think it
has to be juxtaposed with I think that
you rightly say some sort of incentives
change let me let me see it this
differently this I think the merging of
technology and higher human
consciousness is potentially the most
important synergy of the 21st century
technology has this amplification
capacity of exponential 'ti of scale of
power so we're gonna be amplifying
something if we don't amplify if we
amplified these base human tendencies of
greed of anger of hatred
we're in trouble if we amplify love
compassion connection higher states of
human consciousness that's a different
game altogether and I think we can I
agree with the first bit I'm more
skeptical about the second bit the I
think we can why do you think we can I
think we can for a number of reasons the
first is people think psychedelics can
change the world right we've met those
people and meditation people think can
really change some deep sub structures
of the world I think when we start to
understand more about nanotechnology and
hardware and software we're going to
view psychedelics and meditation as
pretty blunt instruments visa vie
what technology may have the capacity to
do stuff is happening and that
trajectory AI um people are creating the
- Julian ostrich from Northeastern
University is creating injecting or at
least attempting to inject unconditional
love into artificial intelligence it's a
project that's taking you know this
really interesting project and that's
not to say they're AI will necessarily
feel love but can it actually be a
mirror for humans by which the human
feels completely accepted in all that
they are the things that are coming out
ultrasonic new modulation loving AI
there is just it there is a host of
tools that people are getting wind of
and emerging Jamie will you know Steven
fire went viral and large part because
of this idea of enlightenment
engineering it's not a perfect solution
so for example as these tools come out
in which we we draw humans to higher
levels of consciousness
someone might create a bless button you
know an Enlightenment button you know
state change on demand that causes all
sorts of ethical issues the flip side of
that what if we created tools that
actually showed us our shadow that
actually we're able to to encourage us
into more and more discomfort it's not
only symmetric like and these are deep
deep discussions that are being had
right in the heart of Silicon Valley as
we speak so part of my push back against
Silicon Valley is the techno utopian
peace that we can just enter VR aware of
anything and everything I think that
itself is pathological I'm at the same
time I don't think we fully understood
the real potential the tech can be in
service too there was AI aligned in the
interview with Douglas rushkoff recently
as a line he was talking about the
psychedelic history of Silicon Valley
and how deeply entwined it was with with
tech he said something like Silicon
Valley dropped acid and now everyone's
having a bad trip yeah if there's
definitely an it's some psychedelic
residue in the way that Silicon Valley
operates that's not necessarily a bad
thing I'm really fascinated by the
dynamics of Silicon Valley and also this
sort of weightlessness
almost like the operating system that we
had before became weightless with with
with the digital world and kind of
exponential tech that suddenly you just
had and that sort of feels very like the
psychedelic experience as well this
one's like a grandiosity of it and the
kind of potentiality of it's like it can
take over the world and it's like well
suddenly we've created these tools where
we can take over the world to use to use
Jimmy wheels expression a lot of the the
world of tech is ecstasy's and
insufficient catharsis it's the
transcendent over the imminent it's this
almost the bypassing the human condition
rather than a deep embodiment of it Tech
is an amplifier of what we are in the
same way that psychedelics are a
nonspecific amplifier
precisely they'll thing with tech is my
argument is they could be probably more
actually more specific amplifiers the
question here in here is man how do we
get healing awakening developing if you
use a Ken Weber's mother will wake up
clean up grow up show up how it can take
be in service of waking up to subtler
levels of reality how can take be in
service of growing up from if ego and
ethnocentric stages of development to
worldcentric stages of development how
you can take being service off of
healing and how can take being serviced
of deeper levels of interconnection and
when I say how can it be in-service the
flip side again is what if it's not what
affects financial potencies are not in
service of those things well you saw
this Saudi Arabia and Iran or drone
strikes
did you see that the the side of the
Saudi oil facilities 50% of Saudi Arabia
oil facilities wait there in a single
day from from half from from a dozen
drones we have exponential capacities
that are being disseminated and
decentralized all it takes is Daniel
Jackson burger speak so this is one or
two non-state actors to use that
capacity of Robotics like drones
synthetic by
cyberterrorism malevolently and then you
have global catastrophic risk
potentialities that these things are all
being built and as a court to go back to
Geralt II as he as he as a balancing act
I think as we increase our capacity to
do harm through tech we also increase
our capacity to do good and
consciousness hacking speaks on this
side of the movement that says hey this
way yeah
what gives you confidence that it's
possible for us to choose the the
positive path rather than the negative
path that we seem to be on at the moment
or is it more of a hope both a couple of
things a lot of the people who I've had
the opportunity to come into contact
with in San Francisco are people who
have been very successful at say gamy
and there's liquidity going this way and
there is also just a deep human need the
eventually we woke up to the fact that
cigarettes were bad for us and stuff
stuff had to change and I think at the
same thing you know the Matins up to
some degree the man does create supply
so I think there's this combination of
people who are at the top of this
so-called tech hierarchy in my
experience wakening up waking up to the
necessity for their shift and the
inevitable rise in people saying hey
like this thing good enough I'm addicted
I'm addicted yeah I emphasize this point
this merging of the the techno mystic I
think is going to be a very key part of
this transition to game be but we need a
holistic reframing of every single part
from the design process to the output
process yeah when you talk you talked
before about kind of the idea of maybe a
button that gave you a kind of peak
state and the dangers of that so a lot
of traditional spirituality or
traditional meditation practice all
about kinda hard the hard work of
getting there and sustaining and and is
there a danger that the all of these are
the technological solutions are just
shortcuts yeah and some people say there
are they they're crutches that will
become reliant upon so I think if we
imagine technology to be something I can
to e to that is currently used in
meditation for example focusing on the
breath it's a tool that we're using as
an object which is eventually meant to
be let go of I think the same with
technology is can we use technology as a
tool that serves a certain purpose along
one's own developmental path and then
when you're ready you can let go so I
think that's what it's really like the
skillful means we did this conference
awaken futures and Mikey Siegel it
founded consciousness hacking you know
really was asking what are the skillful
means of the future or to say a
different way like how good can we get
it really shifting human consciousness
at a personalized level so that that's
the first but I'd say the second bit is
inevitably there are going to be
unintended consequences of benevolent
and nourishing technology for example
people may become addicted to the high
and then we'll need clinics to heal that
that doesn't mean we shouldn't go
forward
it's we have to do a very like serious
cost-benefit analysis and say hey there
are a lot of potentialities and a lot of
potential pitfalls and the other thing
and I spoke to this slightly earlier
this hedonic treadmill that were on of
blessing out we if we build technology
that way not a good thing if we build
with our tools that basically indeed
allow us to dependent our own experience
which by necessity is behold the the
plethora of human experience from
negative to positive that's a different
that's a different innovation altogether
so these can be shortcuts if they're
designed in the wrong way there could be
some sort of non Geo transcendent
function button
that's not what we're calling for here
it's how you do we align our technology
from a place of wisdom and in order to
enhance wisdom and wisdom is not
hedonism I hope you're right you're
skeptical still I'll convince you one
day I feel like yeah what do you make of
it
vote below rebel wisdom is a new sense
making platform bringing together the
most rebellious and inspiring thinkers
from around the world if you're enjoying
our content then you can help us make
more by becoming a subscriber which will
give you access to a load of exclusive
films also you can then join our group
zoom cause to discuss the ideas in the
films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews and if you're a
regular viewer you'll know we talked a
lot about the value of embodying or
actually living out the ideas that we
talk about so that's why we run regular
events in London check out the links on
the website for more and hope to see you
soon
you